- Question: |
    Read the passage below and then answer the questions that follow.

    A lot of students think that learning is only in class. If students use two extra steps, most
    Students will not forget what they learned in class. To achieve effective learning, students
    Needed  to follow two extra steps in the three strategic learning processes.
    The key to success is by following these three strategies. Review is essential to student
    success. Unless content is reviewed by students shortly after It is learned, it will soon be
    forgotten. To avoid forgetting what you learned, it is recommended to review daily.
    It is also recommended to reduce large volumes of notes into point form and to paraphrase
    What you have learned. Other helpful tips include creating concept maps and diagrams;
    Creating fact, concept or vocabulary cards and using visualization to better connect to what
    You learned. These are all important tools to helping students better understand and
    Memorize lesson content.
    The key to achieving academic success cannot be directly correlated to one specific area.
    Rather it requires students to be overall rounded in many different aspects. This includes
    Attending class regularly to keep pace with the class. Falling behind in studies or homework
    Can be detrimental to academic success and can induce stress on to students. Participating
    In class activities and discussions are also vital parts of learning and applying concepts
    learned. On the other hand ,taking good, concise notes will always helping the long run when
    reviewing for tests and exams. To sum it all up, strategic learning is the password for many
    academic achievements. Being exposed to knowledge is the first step in the journey, the fact
    that young scholars can learn and be a part of history is a phenomenal step in furthering their
    search to success. Reviewing  notes, in the way the young individual wishes, by him/herself, or with a good friend, this will help him/her to understand what has been learned in a way he
    understands.
    Lastly practice is a great way to memorise what has been learned, when
    practice achieves its full potential, the individual won’t only been titled for a good mark, but
    also away to view, under and think of things. Those three attributes will help scholars
    become more successful, but it’s important to one as it is to the other, and each and every
    person should find the learning strategies effectual  for  him/herself, and in extremely
    exceptional  occasions even inventor innovate new strategies.
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: a) What does the writer fault in the students thinking according to the first paragraph?
      Answer: The writer faults the fact that the students think that learning is only in class.
      Marks: 2
    - Subquestion: b) Explain the three strategies that are key to success.
      Answer:
        - Review to avoid forgetting what you learned.
        - Reducing large volumes of notes into points for better understanding and memorization.
        - Paraphrasing what you have learned for better understanding and memorization.
      Marks: 6
    - Subquestion: c) Unless content is reviewed by students shortly after it is learned, it will soon be forgotten.
      Answer: If content forgotten is not reviewed by students shortly after it is learnt, it will soon be forgotten.
      Marks: 1
    - Subquestion: "d) The key to achieving academic success cannot be directly correlated to one specific area, can it ? (Proper punctuation; Comma and question mark)"
      Answer: "The key to achieving academic success cannot be directly correlated to one specific area, can it?"
      Marks: 1
    - Subquestion: "e) Discuss the tone of the passage."
      Answer: "Informative. The writer informs the students about the strategies to use in learning."
      Marks: 3
    - Subquestion: "f) According to the passage, identify attributes that help a student become a successful learner."
      Answer:
        - "Reviewing what has been learned."
        - "Attending classes regularly."
        - "Practice for memorization."
      Marks: 2
    - Subquestion: "g) Explain the meaning of the following words and phrases as used in the passage."
      Answer:
        - "Detrimental - damaging"
        - "Connected - connected"
        - "Effectual - effective"
        - "Exceptional - outstanding"
      Marks: 4
  Marks: 20
  QuestionNumber: 1

- Question: |
    Blossoms of the Savannah. Henry ole  Kulet

    Read the excerpt below and answer the questions that follow. (20 marks)
    Her dream was rudely and violently interrupted by a thunderous bang and a loud 
    roar of laughter. She woke up with a start, jumped up to her feet and stared at the 
    door with wide panic-stricken eyes. For a moment she could not figure out her 
    surroundings and called out the name of her sister Taiyo. She was terrified. The 
    door flung open and Olarinkoi staggered in. He was stone drunk. Resian stared at 
    him unblinkingly as he walked towards her and she backed off terrified, squeezing 
    herself flatly against the wall. He followed her there and got hold of her shoulders 
    and shook her violently glaring at her with his glittering eyes.
    “You silly thing,” he thundered angrily. “I tell you to prepare food and you 
    refuse to do so, eh? Today you will know who is the owner of this home. If you 
    are still in doubt, let me tell you frankly that from today on you are my wife, hear 
    that, eh? You are my wife. For a long time you have been sneering at me, showing 
    how highly educated you are. Today we shall see how educated your body is! Yes, 
    we shall see!’’
    He got hold of her hand and began dragging her into the other room. At first 
    she did not understand his intention until he began unfastening her buttons with his 
    rough trembling hands. Then the truth came, and with it, terror and panic. She 
    tried to get away from him, but he held her effortlessly as he brutally continued 
    fumbling with her dress, trying to loosen it. She screamed as loudly as she could 
    while she pushed him away and thrashed frantically about. But that did not deter 
    him and he totally ignored her screams holding her more firmly with his strong 
    arms. Against her loud protest, he tore her garments and began to push her 
    towards the bed.
    Then desperately she took the last chance of self-defence and self-preservation. 
    Mustering all her strength, she thrust his thumb 
    the flesh like a ferocious animal and tenaciously held onto it, tugging at it fiercely 
    like a lioness. She could feel the flesh tearing and she tasted the salt of his blood 
    as it filled her mouth but she clung unto the thumb as Olarinkoi howled with pain.

  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "a) Make notes on the contents of Resian’s dream just before the excerpt."
      Answer:
        - "Resian meets emmakererei, who promises her wonderful things."
        - "Emmakererei promises to take her to Nakuru and join Egerton University."
        - "She promises to offer a vocational job."
        - "She promises to protect her against anyone threatening her with FGM."
        - "She assures her of her right to remain intoiye nemengalana."
      Marks: 4
    - Subquestion: "b) Discuss one character trait of Resian in this excerpt."
      Answer: "Naïve. Resian did not understand his intention until he began unfastening her with his rough trembling hands."
      Marks: 2
    - Subquestion: "c) What has greatly changed in Olarinkoi in this excerpt compared to his earlier conduct in the novel towards Resian?"
      Answer: "Benevolent to malevolent. Olarinkoi has turned into a monster and rapist yet he had worn a protective, caring, and mindful face to Resian and her sister and actually saved them from Ntara and Lante."
      Marks: 3
    - Subquestion: "d) Identify and illustrate two aspects of style in this excerpt."
      Answer:
        - "Use of dialogue 'you silly thing,' he thundered angrily."
        - "Use of simile 'Sunk her teeth into the flesh like a ferocious animal.'"
      Marks: 4
    - Subquestion: "e) Explain two major issues raised in the excerpt."
      Answer:
        - "Plight of women. Women are subjected to physical, sexual, and emotional harassment by male counterparts."
        - "Male chauvinism. Olarinkoi thinks he has the right to molest Resian because she is a woman."
      Marks: 4
    - Subquestion: "f) Explain what happens immediately after the excerpt."
      Answer: "Resian bites Olarinkoi’s thumb, nearly severing the limb. She is hit on the ribcage and head until she passes out."
      Marks: 3
    - Subquestion: "g) 'Today we shall see how educated your body is' Rewrite in reported speech."
      Answer: "He said that they would see how educated her body was."
      Marks: 1
    - Subquestion: "h) Explain the meaning of the following expressions in the passage."
      Answer:
        - "Unblinkingly - forthright."
        - "Effortlessly - easily."
        - "Mustering - collecting."
        - "Howled - wept/cried loudly."
      Marks: 4
  Marks: 25
  QuestionNumber: 2

- Question: |
    Read the poem below carefully and answer the questions that follow.
    WHAT’S IMPORTANT IN LIFE?
    The Years have passed by,
    In the blink of an eye,
    Moments of sadness,
    And joy have flown by.

    People I loved,
    Have come and have gone,
    But the world never stopped,
    And we all carried on.

    Life wasn't easy,
    And the struggles were there,
    Filled with times that it mattered,
    Times I just didn't care.

    I stood on my own,
    And I still found my way,
    Through some nights filled with tears,
    And the dawn of new days.

    And now with old age,
    It's become very clear,
    Things I once found important,
    Were not why I was here.

    And how many things,
    That I managed to buy,
    Were never what made me,
    Feel better inside.

    And the worries and fears,
    That plagued me each day,
    In the end of it all,
    Would just fade away.

    But how much I reached out,
    To others when needed,
    Would be the true measure,
    Of how I succeeded.

    And how much I shared,
    Of my soul and my heart,
    Would ultimately be,
    What set me apart.

    And what's really important
    Is my opinion of me,
    And whether or not,
    I'm the best I can be.

    And how much more kindness,
    And love I can show,
    Before the Lord tells me,
    It's my time to go.

    By Pat Fleming 

  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "a) Who is the persona in the poem above?"
      Answer: "An old person who has gone through different stages of life and wonders whether her life’s experiences were fulfilling."
      Marks: 2
    - Subquestion: "b) What subject matter is addressed in the poem?"
      Answer: "Life contentment. The persona has gone through struggles but with old age, he has become wiser and is living a fulfilled life."
      Marks: 3
    - Subquestion: "c) Give evidence from the poem suggesting that time has elapsed quickly."
      Answer:
        - "Years have passed by."
        - "In the blink of an eye."
      Marks: 3
    - Subquestion: "d) Paraphrase verse 6 of the poem."
      Answer: "The financial status of the persona determining what she was able to acquire is not what defined the persona’s character."
      Marks: 2
    - Subquestion: "e) Describe the attitude of the persona toward the subject matter."
      Answer: "The persona has a critical and analytic attitude towards the subject matter. He interrogates how he has lived through different stages of life till he has become old."
      Marks: 3
    - Subquestion: "f) Identify and explain the stylistic device employed in the last verse of the poem."
      Answer: "Euphemism – 'It’s my time to go' meaning it’s my time to die."
      Marks: 2
    - Subquestion: "g) With old age, it’s become very clear. Rewrite ending with: old age) (1 mark)"
      Answer: "With old age, it’s become very clear."
      Marks: 1
    - Subquestion: "h) Explain the meaning of the following as used in the poem."
      Answer:
        - "Plagued - troubled."
        - "I stood on my own, through some nights filled with tears - independent."
        - "True measure - real yardstick."
        - "howled - wept/cried loudly."
      Marks: 4
  Marks: 20
  QuestionNumber: 3

- Question: Answer the following questions.
  Subquestions:
    - Subquestion: "A. Fill in with the most suitable prepositions"
      Answer:
        - "They acquainted Jean with Italian prepositions."
        - "It was naive of you to ignore the doctor’s prescription."
        - "This team is brilliant at her everyday work."
      Marks: 3
    - Subquestion: "B. Punctuate accordingly"
      Answer:
        - "She was beautiful, kind, intelligent, and young."
        - "China, one of the most powerful nations on earth, has a huge population."
      Marks: 2
    - Subquestion: "C. Rewrite according to instructions in brackets"
      Answer:
        - "Walking from home to school, I met my friend."
        - "Physics was taught to you by whom?"
        - "Rather than giving the money to my sister, I gave it to my cousin."
      Marks: 3
    - Subquestion: "D. Having persevered, he bore fruits. (Rewrite using “perseverance”)"
      Answer: "He bore fruits because of his perseverance."
      Marks: 1
    - Subquestion: "E. Use the most appropriate form of the verb in brackets"
      Answer:
        - "What were the children doing when you last saw them?"
        - "I didn’t appreciate his jokes. They were not funny."
      Marks: 2
    - Subquestion: "F. Rewrite the sentences using the words in brackets"
      Answer:
        - "He did not say anything useful."
        - "Is there no one to answer this question?"
      Marks: 2
    - Subquestion: "G. Fill with the most appropriate collective noun"
      Answer:
        - "A regiment of soldiers received medals from the president."
        - "A cluster of islands was submerged in the ocean when the cyclone occurred."
      Marks: 2
  Marks: 15
  QuestionNumber: 4

